Finding Aid for the Nancy Baden Collection about Brazilian Literature LSC.0436
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nancy Baden Collection about Brazilian Literature
1969-2000
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0436
1 unknown (2 boxes, 1 flat oversized box, 1 legal-size document box, 1 letter-size document box, and 2 shoeboxes)
Nancy Baden was a professor of Spanish and Portuguese at Cal State Fullerton. Much of her work concentrated on Jorge Amado and literature produced under the period of Brazilian censorship. This collection consists of books that are either by or about Jorge Amado, letters and cards by Amado, interview materials related to censorship in Brazilian literature, and card catalogs on Brazilian literature.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Baden, December 2003.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9970472813606533
Biography/History
Nancy Baden was a professor of Spanish and Portuguese at Cal State Fullerton from 1969 until 2003. Much of her work concentrated on Jorge Amado and literature produced under the period of Brazilian censorship. She published a book on the latter topic in 1999 titled The Muffled Cries: The Writer and Literature in Authoritarian Brazil 1964-1985. Raised in Brazil, Baden attended UCLA where she received a Ph.D. in Hispanic Languages and Literatures. In the 1960s, while Baden was still a UCLA graduate student, she began a correspondence with Amado that lasted until the mid-1990s. In 1969 she began teaching at Cal State Fullerton and eventually became Chair of the Department of Foreign Languages and Literatures. While at Cal State Fullerton Baden helped establish both the Portuguese and TESOL (Teaching of English to Speakers of Other Languages) programs and served as the President of the Friends of the Fullerton Arboretum from 2001-2003.
Scope and Content
This collection contains of books that are by or about Jorge Amado—many of which are autographed by Amado and given to Baden. Also included are letters and cards written by Amado, research and interview materials on censorship in Brazilian literature consisting of audio cassette interviews with writers and artists, notes, interview questions and other files, as well as card catalogs Baden maintained on Brazilian literature.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
1. Jorge Amado -- books, letters and 1983 interview
2. Interview materials on censorship in Brazilian literature
3. Card catalogs on Brazilian literature
Nancy T., Baden -- Archives
- Jorge Amado, 1969-2000; 1 boxes 1 document box and 1 oversized box
  Scope and Content
  Books from Nancy Baden's collection, a number of which are autographed. Almost all of them are by or about Jorge Amado.
  - Jorge Amado 80 Anos de Vida e Obra: Subsídios para Pesquisa. Organização, texto, pesquisa Rosane Rubim, Maried Carniero., 1992 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Tieta do Agreste by Jorge Amado, 1977 (Box 1, Item 2)
    Autographed by Jorge Amado.
  - Tereza Batista cansada de guerra by Jorge Amado, 1972 (Box 1, Item 3)
    Scope and Content note
    Autographed by Jorge Amado, 1st edition.
  - Bahia, a cidade de Jorge Amado: Atas do ciclo de palestras, 2000 (Box 1, Item 4)
    Scope and Contents
    An edited compilation of a lecture series
  - Jorge Amado: O Homem e a Obra Presença em Portugal by Álvaro Salema, 1982 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - O Menino Grapiúna by Jorge Amado, Undated (Box 1, Item 6)
    Autographed by Jorge Amado. Edition 9991 of 11,000 print run.
  - Bahia de Todos os Santos: Guia de Ruas e Mistérios by Jorge Amado, 1977 (Box 1, Item 7)
    Autographed by Jorge Amado and Carlos Bastos.
  - Um grapiúna no país do carnival, 2000 (Box 1, Item 8)
    Edited work on proceedings of a Jorge Amado Studies symposium
  - O Gato Malhado e a Andorinha Sinhá: Uma Historia de Amor by Jorge Amado, 1976 (Box 1, Item 9)
  - Uma Casa de Palavras by Myriam Fraga, 1997 (Box 1, Item 10)
  - 1 Simposio Internacional De Estudos Sobre Jorge Amado: Um Grapiúna no País do Carnaval, 1983 (Box 1, Item 11)
    Symposium folder containing reprint of "Journal of Latin American Lore" published by UCLA Latin American Center, typewritten list of interview questions and answers, letters to Nancy Baden, printed materials, symposium program and press clipping.
  - Jorge Amado letters and cards, Ca. 1969-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letters and cards from Jorge Amado received by Nancy Baden.
  - Jorge Amado Interview, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Interview questionnaire re: Brazilian censorship completed by Jorge Amado.
  - Jorge Amado and Nancy Baden photographs, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Black and white photograph of Nancy Baden and Jorge Amado taken at Jorge Amado's house in 1983. Color photograph of Jorge Amado's 80th birthday party in 1992. Annotated xerox copies of each included.
  - Iconografia dos Deuses Africanos no Candomblé da Bahia., 1980 December (Box 2, Item 1)
    128 oversized colorplates depicting the costume, rites, celebrations, musical instruments and other cultural artifacts relating to Candomblé, the Afro-Brazilian religion centered in Bahia, Brazil. Illustrations by Carybé, text by Jorge Amado, Pierre Verger, and Waldeloir Rego. This copy is autographed by Carybé and Amado. Only 5000 copies printed. Oversize.
- Interview materials on censorship in Brazilian literature, Ca. 1983-1984
  This series contains material related to interviews of Brazilian artists and writers that Baden conducted. Includes notes, questions and audio cassette recordings.
  - Oswaldo Franca Junior - Belo, 1983 July 14 (Box 3, Item 1)
    Audio cassette recording of interview.
  - José Loureiro - Rio, 1983 July 17 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - José Loureiro - Rio, 1983 July 17 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Antonio Torres - Rio, 1983 July 19 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Adonias Filho - Rio, 1983 July 19 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Roberto Drummond - Belo Horizente, 1984 May 26 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Heloísa Buarque de Hollanda - Fullerton, 1984 July 11 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Lydia Fagundes Telles, Undated (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Ignácio Loyola Brandão, Undated (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Interviews (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    3.5 inch floppy disk.
    Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Interview materials (Folder 1 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    File contains list of Brazilian writers Baden interviewed and completed interview forms containing both typescript questions and the subjects' responses.
  - Interview materials (Folder 2 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Typescript and hand written interview materials including a blank questionnaire template, lists of questions, handwritten notes and handwritten transcribed interviews.
- Card catalogs on Brazilian literature
  - Card catalog (Box 1 of 2), Undated (Box 4)
    A card catalogue consisting of typescript and handwritten index cards organized by topic as well as by author. Some of the topics include: Portuguese-American literature, Brazilian theater, and poetry.
  - Card catalog (Box 2 of 2), Undated (Box 5)